Guide to the Walter W. Williams Papers, 1916-1987
Williams, Walter W. papers, 1916-1987
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Walter W. Williams Papers 1916-87
6547
Williams, Walter Wilkinson, 1892-.
1.0 cubic ft.
correspondence, newsclippings, books and photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
This collection contains correspondence, newsclippings and research notes. Most of the research is related to the study of fertility and sterility.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Walter Wilkinson Williams was born on January 28, 1892. He attended Cornell University from 1909-1915. He received a bachelor of arts in 1913 from the Cornell University College of Arts and Sciences. In 1915, he received a Doctorate in Veterinary Medicine also from Cornell University. He married Glady Howell Warrick in 1916. They had two children Walter Jr., (1918) and Rosalind (1923). Walter Jr. was a 1941 graduate of Cornell University.
Williams practiced veterinary medicine for thirteen years. From 1920-25 he studied bovine semen and spermatic pathology. He collaborated on his father Walter Long Williams' book The Diseases of the Genital Organs of Domestic Animals. In 1928, at the age of 36, he decided to go back to school in order to receive a medical degree. He published a book entitled Sex Hygiene and Reproduction of Cattle, in 1929, which helped to finance his education. He graduated in 1933, from the Albany Medical College, where he received his doctorate in medicine. After this he moved to Springfield, Massachusetts, where he served as house officer at Springfield Hospital. By 1940, he had devoted his medical practice to the study of infertility and sterility.
From 1944-46, during World War II, he served as a surgeon with the rank of Lieutenant Commander for the U.S. Navy. For many years after the war, he was a clinical geneticist. He was awarded the Gold Medal Award in 1951, by the American Medical Association for an exhibit on the diagnostic and prognostic procedures of fertility and sterility. In 1953, he was given an honorary mention by the American College of Obstetrics and Gynecology for an exhibit on the diagnosis of fertility. Between 1925-1975 he published approximately 100 articles on male and female sterility. By 1977, he had published 30 more. He is author of Sterility: The Diagnostic Survey of the Infertile Couple, first published in 1953 with two subsequent editions. From 1958-1961, he served as the editor of the International Journal of Fertility. In 1977, at the age of 84, he published, An Insight into Marital Infertility. His accomplishments include co-founding the American Fertility Society in 1944. He was an honorary member, founder and past president of the American Society for the Study of Sterility. He was also an honorary member and founder of the International Fertility Association. He was an honorary member of the Sociedad de Obstetricia y Gynecologia de Venezuela, the Societats Gynecologica et Obstertrica Italica, and the American College of Theriogenologists. He was a member of the American Medical Association, Hampden District Medical Society, the New England Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology, and the American College of Obstetrics and Gynecology.
He died in 1988 in Longmeadow, Massachusetts.
For more biographical information, please see "Contributions to Infertility Studies" in the biographical series of this collection. This is an autobiographical sketch included in Part IV of the third edition of his book, Sterility: The Diagnostic Survey of the Infertile Couple.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection includes personal material such as newsclippings, correspondence and photographs, as well as research material, printed material, slides and photographs relating to Williams' infertility work. Personal correspondence includes letters from Walter W. William's father Walter Long Williams, one of the first six professors of the New York State College of Veterinary Medicine at Cornell University. Materials related to his work on infertility in both animals and humans include numerous publications, research notes, charts and tables. Many diagrams and research notes are from his book, Infertility: A Guide for the Childless Couple.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Williams, Walter Wilkinson, 1892-.; Williams, Walter Long, 1856-1945.; New York State College of Veterinary Medicine.
Subjects:
Physicians.; Veterinarians.; Infertility
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
Besides numerous academic journal articles, Walter W. Williams also published a number of books which can be found in the Cornell University library catalog. These books include The Diseases of the Genital Organs of Domestic Animals (1921) which was written primarily by his father Walter L. Williams with his collaboration and assistance.The book Sex Hygiene and Reproduction of Cattle, was written in 1930. It was followed by Sterility; The Diagnostic Survey of the Infertile Couple which was written in 1953. His last book, An Insight Into Marital Infertility, was published in 1977.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical Material
Folders 1-5, 46-47
Series II. Correspondence
Folders 6-10
Series III. Writings
Folders 11-16
Series IV. Research Material & Subject Files
Folders 17-45
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Material
  - Newspaper clippings and magazine articles, 1953-84 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Contributions to Infertility Studies", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bibliographies, ca. 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Congress Venezolano de Obstetrcia y Ginecologica-Mexico, 1945, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Journal of Fertility - Festschrift in Honor of Walter W. Williams, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Navy and World War I, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Dr. Leopoldo Aguerrevere medal, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series II.Correspondence
  - W.L. Williams, 1916-25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - W.L. Williams, 1927-43 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Walter W. Williams Jr., 1938-40 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American College of Theriogenologists (A.C.T.), 1983-86 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1918-87 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III. Writings
  - Journal Articles and Publications
    - General, 1921-25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General, 1927-39 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General, 1940-48 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General, 1950-58 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General, 1960-69 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - General, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Books
    - Sex Hygiene and Reproduction of Cattle-annotated, 1930 (Box 1)
    - An Insight into Marital Infertility-annotated, 1977 (Box 1)
    - La Sterilita: Diagnosi e Terapiia dell'inferilita coniugale, 1960 (Box 1)
- Series IV. Research Material and Subject Files
  - Notes on spermatozoa, 1920's (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Physiologic Factors Concomitant to Maturation of the Ovum, Fertilization, Implantation and Survival", 1942-1943, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Pathogogical Spermatozoa and Fertility Potential" (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Semen and sperm analysis and charts (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Spermatic Cytopathoogy and Potenial Fertility" (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Progress on Infertility" and other notes (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Anovulation articles and material (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Hyperestrogenic Anovulation", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Effects of Low Dosage Irradiation on Ovarian Function", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Diagnosis and Therapy of Endometriosis" (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Basal body temperature, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Foundation of the American Fertility Society" (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Chapter X: Basic Progress in Marital Infertility", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes for Sterility: The Diagnostic Survey of Infertile Couples, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Infertility Research, 1980's (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Book notices and reviews for Sterility, 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Resolve, Inc, 1975-76 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The American Society for the Study of Sterility, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Anovulation Charts, ca, 1942-1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Charts recording basal body temperature, ca. 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Charts and tables related to ovulation, ca. 1947 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Diagrams of abnormal sperm, ca. 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Diagrams of normal sperm, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Articles by Eric Bloom, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous journal articles on spermatozoa, 1921-1938 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous journal articles on spermatozoa, 194-1946, 1974, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Laboratory Manuals, 1919, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Exhibits, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Slides, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Three photographs have been physically separated from this collection. They are housed in the Veterinary Photograph Collection, and have been assigned the folling numbers:
VPC.00??? Walter W. Williams in uniform at Sampson Naval Training Station, June 1945.
VPC.00??? Walter W. Williams, Dr. Mayer and Dr. Percival A. Duff at Sampson Naval Training Station, May 1945.
VPC.00??? Portrait of Walter W. Williams, ca. 1940-1949.